Hello everyone, and welcome to the
Minecraft Transit Railway tutorials,
new and updated for 4.0.0.
In this episode, we will cover everything you
need to know to get your very
first railway up and running.
Let's get started!
One of the main goals of Minecraft Transit Railway
is to provide fully automated train operation.
Unlike other railway mods in Minecraft,
train spawning and movement is
programmed from a centralised dashboard.
Simulation occurs whether
world chunks are loaded or not.
Therefore, there are four main
components to a railway system.
Rails, stations, routes, and depots.
Let's see how these pieces come together.
There are a few categories of rails.
Normal two-way rails allow trains
to move on them in both directions,
while one-way rails only allow
movement in one direction.
These rails have a speed
limit associated with them.
Platform and siding rails belong
to the specialised category.
Platforms are where trains can open their
doors and pick up and drop off passengers.
Sidings are where trains spawn
and start and finish their routes.
Turn back rails also belong to this
category and they allow trains to
change directions in the middle of a route.
Let's start with a very basic layout.
We will build a siding rail, two platform rails,
and some normal two-way rails to
connect everything up like this.
We will then programme the train to spawn
at the siding, move to the first platform,
move to the second platform,
then return to the siding.
To build this in Minecraft, we will need
some Rail Nodes and Rail Connectors.
Place down two Rail Nodes
and use the Rail Connector
to right-click the two nodes to build the rail.
Rail Nodes can be oriented in different directions
which will determine the shape of the rail.
Here are some examples of straight
tracks, S-curves, and 90° curves.
To remove a rail, simply break the
Rail Nodes or use the Rail Remover
by right-clicking on the nodes of the track.
Now we will build the siding rail.
An important thing to note is that
the length of the rail must be at
least the length of the train we want to spawn.
For this tutorial, let's build a siding of 40 m.
Next, we will build the two platform rails.
Generally, the platform should
be the same length as the siding.
So, let's build them 40 m long.
Finally, let's connect everything
up with the two-way Rail Connector.
For this tutorial, we will
enforce a speed limit of 80 km/h.
Let's go back to our track diagram.
As we mentioned, the train should spawn
at the siding, move to the first platform,
move to the second platform,
then return to the siding.
To programme our trains to follow this
pattern, we will use the Railway Dashboard.
Right-click the Railway Dashboard item to open it.
On the left, there are three tabs:
"Stations", "Routes", and "Depots".
The "Stations" tab is currently selected.
On the right, there is a map of the world.
We can use the zoom buttons on the bottom right
corner or the scroll wheel to zoom in and out.
The blue dot marks our current location
and clicking and dragging on
the map moves the map around.
Let's get started by defining a station area.
Click on "Add Station".
Click and drag on the map to draw
a rectangular area for the station.
We will call the first station Desert Plains.
Press "Done" when finished.
We will do the same thing for the
second station called South Sand Bay.
Next, we will create a route
for the trains to run on.
Let's head over to the "Routes"
tab and click on "Add Route".
We will call it "Line 1||Outbound" for now.
Anything after the two pipe characters
is considered the route variation.
The pipe character can be typed
by pressing Shift+Backslash.
When we zoom into the first station that we
have created, we will see a small white square.
This represents the platform
rail that we just built.
Click on this square to add it to our route.
Notice that the station name
now appears on the left.
Let's do the same for the
second platform we built.
This one is at the second station.
Clicking on it adds the
station to the left as well.
Press "Done" when finished.
Finally, we need to make a depot so
that our trains can appear in the world.
Go to the "Depots" tab.
Notice how the stations and platforms disappeared,
but our siding showed up as a small white square.
Let's click on "Add Depot" and draw
a rectangular area over the siding.
Don't forget to type in a descriptive name
for the depot and press "Done" when finished.
By default, the siding will have
no train associated with it.
Click on the siding, which also
appears as a small white square
to configure the train cars that will be spawned.
Under selected vehicle, click "Edit".
For this tutorial, we will start with
a cab car in the forward orientation,
some trailers, and finally a cab
car in the backward orientation.
Keep in mind that each car has a set length.
Because our siding is 40 m, we can
only fit a few cars on the siding.
We can see the length of each
car in the train selection menu.
We will also set the maximum
trains on the siding to 1 for now.
To make our depot functional,
we will need to edit it.
On the left pane, hover over the depot and click
on the edit button, which looks like a pencil.
First, we will click on "Edit Instructions".
We need to assign our route to the depot
so that the trains will know where to go.
On the left, there are 24 sliders,
one for each in-game hour.
Each slider will determine the maximum
frequency at which trains will leave the depot.
For example, if I set it to
2.5 trains per Minecraft hour,
it means that the trains will depart the
depot no less than 20 real-time seconds apart.
Bear in mind that this defines the maximum
frequency, meaning that if there are no
trains left in the depot, nothing will leave
the depot even after 20 seconds have passed.
Finally, click on "Refresh Path" to generate
the actual path trains will take on our railway.
It is very important to click this button every
time we change something such as the
track layout or train instructions.
Press Esc on the keyboard
to return to the Dashboard
and press Esc again to return to the game.
The train should start departing from the siding.
To see upcoming arrivals and a
system map of the whole network,
open the Railway Dashboard again
and click on "Transport System Map".
When clicking on Desert Plains,
we can see the upcoming arrivals.
At South Sand Bay, since
all trains are terminating,
we can tick the "Show Terminating"
box to see the arrivals.
In the "Routes" tab, we can click on our route and
see the live train positions for Line
1 with the route variation "Outbound".
Let's go back to Minecraft.
Unfortunately, there is one problem.
The train doors are not opening, so
there is no way to board the trains.
Platform blocks, Automatic Platform Gates,
and Platform Screen Doors can be used
to tell the train which doors to open.
For this tutorial, we will place
Platform blocks along our platform rail.
Notice that only the doors next
to Platform blocks will open.
Congratulations, our first
railway system is complete!
If this tutorial has helped you so far,
remember to subscribe to the channel!
Earlier, we configured our
siding to only spawn one train.
If we have more than one train on our
system, there is a risk of jamming.
Also, passengers can take the train
from Desert Plains to South Sand Bay,
but not the other way around because trains
at South Sand Bay go straight to the siding.
To fix this, let's modify our setup a little.
First, let's build a second platform
at Desert Plains for inbound trains
and connect this platform to the main route.
Next, we will rename the platform to "2".
Let's set up a second route
called "Line 1||Inbound".
Just like before, we will select
our platforms for this route.
We will also copy the route colour
from the "Outbound" variation so
that the two route variations, "Inbound"
and "Outbound", will be grouped together.
Now head over to the "Depots" tab, click on the
siding, and tick the "Unlimited Vehicles" box.
Edit the depot and add the
"Inbound" route to our instructions.
Let's also reduce the frequencies a bit.
Remember to click "Refresh Path" again.
With our current setup, more than one train
can run through the system without jamming,
and passengers can now travel from
South Sand Bay back to Desert Plains.
Let's see how this looks in game.
We can just walk right on when the
doors are open to ride the train.
We can also go back to the Transport System
Map to look at the arrivals and routes.
Thank you everyone for watching the first episode
of the Minecraft Transit
Railway Tutorials for 4.0.0.
Today we learned how to set up our very
first railway by building rails and
configuring the stations, routes, and
depots through the Railway Dashboard.
In the next episode, we will explore other modes
of transport and important
blocks for our stations.
If you enjoyed this tutorial, please remember
to like the video and subscribe to the channel,
and comment down below if you
have any questions for me.
I have put some useful links
down in the description as well,
so be sure to take a look at that.
Thank you so much for watching and
I'll see you in the next video.